

🛮 216-544-8680 | 🔀 itsxiaoliu.cs@gmail.com | 🌴 xiao-liu.me | 🖸 liuxiao1468 | 🛅 xiao-leo-liu-1a5bb3112

Summary.

I am a senior Computer Science Ph.D student and I work with Prof. Heni Ben Amor at Interactive Robotics Lab in School of Computing and Augmented Intelligence at Arizona State University. My research is focusing on Robot Learning, Representation Learning, and their applications in Embodied AI and Human-robot Interaction (HRI). Several publications of my research are/were shown at ICRA, IROS, and CoRL. Currently, my research interests have shifted towards exploring methods to empower large language models (LLMs) to operate as reasoning system and distill knowledge for robot learning.

Education

Arizona State University Tempe, Arizona

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE, ADVISOR: PROF. HENI BEN AMOR

Aug. 2019 - May. 2024 • Thesis Focus: Robot Learning via Deep State-Space Modeling GPA: 4.0/4.0

Case Western Reserve University

M.S. IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING, ADVISOR: PROF. KIJU LEE Aug. 2016 - May. 2019

Thesis Focus: Automated Facial Emotion Recognition for Human-Robot Interaction GPA: 3.8/4.0

Southwest Jiaotong University

B.S. IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING Aug. 2011 - May. 2015

Project: Fault Diagnosis of Roller Bearing Based on Wavelet Analysis GPA: 3.6/4.0

Experience

RadiusAl, Inc. Tempe, Arizona

COMPUTER VISION DATA SCIENTIST (PART-TIME)

Sep. 2020 - Dec 2023

- Refined Multi-object tracking (MOT) algorithms using Bayes Filter for Video Analytics for indoor and outdoor cameras, improved ~9% accuracy.
- Developed multi-objective optimization technique base on Frank-Wolfe algorithm for monocular depth prediction model across multiple datasets.
- · Researched on monocular depth prediction models with varied advanced architecture, Vision Transformer and multi-scale local planar guidance blocks, achieved depth estimation with 0.117, 0.416 on abs REL and RMS error metrics and 0.868 on d1 metric on NYU depth testset.

Interactive Robtoics Lab, ASU

Tempe, Arizona

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

June. 2020 - Present

- Developed state-space modeling for long-horizon robot learning within Large Language models (LLMs), where LLMs perform planning and reasoning while maintaining state tracking.
- Embodied AI: Proposed Diff-Control, an Action diffusion policy incorporating ControlNet from the domain of image generation to robot actions. [S1]
- Created a multimodal learning framework (α-MDF) using attention mechanism and differentiable filtering, which conducts state estimation in latent space with multiple modalities. [C5]
- Developed differentiable Ensemble Kalman Filters (DEnKF) framework incorporating algorithmic priors for robot learning, i.e., learning system dynamics from observations, and learning representations from high-dimensional space. [C4]
- Deployed the differentiable filtering framework with smartwatch for ubiquitous robot control tasks, i.e., teleoperation, drone piloting. [C6]

Case Western Reserve University

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Aug. 2017 - Aug. 2019

- Led social robot project "Woody and Philos" project, developed advanced algorithms in Computer Vision for social robots. [C2]
- Real-time Human Facial Emotion Expression Recognition for Human-robot Interaction using deep learning and machine learning technique. (featured on Case Western Daily) [C1] [J1]
- · Human-Robot Interaction: Developed social robots-"Philos" & "Woody" platform and investigated the potential of social robots as cognitive assessment applications for older adults. (featured on ideastream)
- Human-centered Al: Collaborated on hardware and algorithm development for the vision-based Tangible Geometric Games- "e-Cube" for cognitive skills assessment.

CWRU & ASU

Cleveland, Ohio & Tempe, Arizona

TEACHING ASSISTENT

2018 - 2019, 2023 - 2024

- Served as the teaching assistant for EMAE250 (Computers in Mechanical Engineering), instructing students on numerical problem-solving using Matlab and providing guidance throughout the learning process.
- TA for CSE205 (Object Oriented Programming), instructing students on conding with varied data structure and OOP tasks in Java.

XIAO LIU · CV APRIL 28, 2024

Uber Technologies, Inc. Xi'an, China

DATA ANALYSTJan. 2016 - Aug. 2016

· Coordinated data analysis and fraud detection with the operation team. Conducted competitor tracking and advising on driver incentives.

Hitachi, Ltd. Chengdu, China

DESIGN ENGINEER June 2015 - Dec. 2015

Assisted in product development by analyzing cable and power converter sizing, heat release, and power supply design. Revised design parameters
to meet customer requirements and national standards while optimizing manufacturing and logistical processes for cost reduction.

Publications

2024	[\$1], Liu, X, Zhou, Y, Weigend, F, Sonawani, S & Ben Amor, H. "Diff-Control: A Stateful Diffusion-based Policy for Imitation Learning" <i>IEEE/RSJ IROS (under review)</i>	IROS 2024
2024	[W2], Liu, X, Weigend, F, Zhou, Y & Ben Amor, H. "Enabling Stateful Behaviors for Diffusion-based Policy Learning" ICRA 2024 Workshop - Back to the Future: Robot Learning Going Probabilistic	ICRA 2024
2024	[C6], Weigend, F, Liu, X, Sonawani, S & Ben Amor, H. "iRoCo: Intuitive Robot Control from Anywhere using a Smartwatch" <i>IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)</i>	ICRA 2024
2023	[W2], Liu, X, Zhou, Y, Ikemoto, S & Ben Amor, H. "Multimodal Learning of Soft Robot Dynamics using Differentiable Filters" <i>CoRL 2023 Workshop on Learning for Soft Robots</i>	CoRL 2023
2023	[C5] , Liu, X, Zhou, Y, Ikemoto, S & Ben Amor, H. " α -MDF: An Attention-based Multimodal Differentiable Filter for Robot State Estimation" 7th Conference on Robot Learning	CoRL 2023
2023	[W1], Weigend, F, Liu, X, & Ben Amor, H. "Probabilistic Differentiable Filters Enable Ubiquitous Robot Control with Smartwatches" <i>IROS 2023 Workshop on Differentiable Probabilistic Robotics</i>	IROS 2023
2023	[C4] , Liu, X, Clark, G, Campbell, J, Zhou, Y & Ben Amor, H. "Enhancing State Estimation in Robots: A Data-Driven Approach with Differentiable Ensemble Kalman Filters" <i>IEEE/RSJ IROS</i>	IROS 2023
2023	[C3], Liu, X, Ikemoto, S, Yoshimitsu, Y & Ben Amor, H. "Learning Soft Robot Dynamics using Differentiable Kalman Filters and Spatio-Temporal Embeddings" <i>IEEE/RSJ IROS</i>	IROS 2023
2021	[J1], Liu, X, Cheng, X & Lee, K. "GA and SVM based Facial Emotion Recognition using Geometric Features" <i>IEEE</i> sensors Journal on Machine Vision and automated systems	IEEE sensors 2021
2020	[C2], Hayosh D, Liu, X & Lee, K. "Woody: Low-Cost Open-source Humanoid Torso Robot" <i>IEEE 17th International Conference on Ubiquitous Robots (UR)</i>	UR 2020
2020	[C1], Liu, X & Lee, K. "Optimized Facial Emotion Recognition Technique for Assessing User Experience" <i>IEEE Games Entertainment and Medias Conference (GEM)</i>	GEM 2020

Skills

• Programming: Python, C/C++, Java; Tools & Library: PyTorch, TensorFlow, OpenCV, ROS, Matlab, MuJoCo, Unity, Docker, Git, Kubernetes;

References

Heni Ben Amor Tempe, Arizona

Associate Professor, Ph.D. Advisor

Arizona State University

• School of Computing and Augmented Intelligence | Google DeepMind Researcher Tel: 480.965.2253, Email: hbenamor@asu.edu

Kiju Lee College Station, Texa

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR, M.S. ADVISOR

Texas A&M University

• Engineering Technology and Industrial Distribution and Mechanical Engineering Tel: 979.458.6479, Email: kiju.lee@tamu.edu

Wenlong ZhangASSOCIATE PROFESSOR, Ph.D. COMMITTEE MEMBER

Mesa, Arizona
Arizona State University

RadiusAl

• School of Manufacturing Systems and Networks at the Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering Email: Wenlong, Zhang@asu.edu

Aykut Dengi Tempe, Arizona

CEO, Industry advisor

• Co-founder, Co-CEO, and Board Member, RadiusAl Tel: 480.540.1349, Email: aykut.dengi@radius.ai